<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Observations upon a sermon intituled, A confutation of atheism from the faculties of the soul, alias̀, Matter and motion cannot think preached April 4, 1692 : by way of refutation.</title>
            <author>Layton, Henry, 1622-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49843</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L756</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39115</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18214479</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18214479</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107183</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49843)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107183)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1126:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Observations upon a sermon intituled, A confutation of atheism from the faculties of the soul, alias̀, Matter and motion cannot think preached April 4, 1692 : by way of refutation.</title>
                  <author>Layton, Henry, 1622-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Henry Layton.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bentley, Richard, 1662-1742. --  Matter and motion cannot think.</term>
               <term>Christianity and atheism --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Atheism --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107183:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>OBSERVATIONS upon a Sermon Intituled, <hi>A Confutation of Atheiſm from the Faculties of the Soul,</hi> aliàs, <hi>Matter and Motion cannot think:</hi> Preached April 4. 1692.</head>
            <p>By way of REFUTATION.</p>
            <p>THE whole Sermon is comprehended in 39 pages, the firſt 12 of which, or to page 12, are employed as an Introduction or <hi>Apparatus</hi> to his Text and Deſign: and page 12, the Preacher ſays, he intends to prove, that <hi>the Life, Motion, Eſſence and Nature of Man is derived from God, and may direct Men to the knowledge of him:</hi> but all this need not be proved to Men of my opinion, who do willingly agree the Truth of his Aſſertion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 13. he ſays he will prove, That <hi>there is an Immaterial Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in Man, which we call Soul and Spirit, eſſentially diſtinct from our Bodies.</hi> And this if he ſhall ſubſtantially perform, it ſhall paſs for heroic and above all ordinary power; but preſently he ſeeks to avoid and ſhift off his performance of Proving, by ſaying, that the thing is <hi>evident in it ſelf.</hi> But this I do utterly deny, and think the contrary more evident, <hi>viz. That the humane Soul is a material Spirit generated, growing, and falling with the Body, and riſing again with it at the ſound of the voice of the Archangel, and the trump of God.</hi> And upon this Difference between our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, the ſtate of our preſent Controverſie will depend. I have denied this his Aſſertion, That <hi>the thing is ſelf-evident.</hi> Why, but ſays he, <hi>There is ſomething in Man's Compoſition that thinks, deliberates, conſents and actuates all humane Senſations and Powers; theſe Activities cannot come from nothing, therefore they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107183:2"/>come from an immaterial Soul or Spirit in Man.</hi> To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, his Conſequence is not good; <hi>viz.</hi> Theſe Powers come from ſomething, <hi>ergo,</hi> from an Immaterial Spirit: for they may come from a Material Spirit. In proof whereof I argue <hi>à ſimili:</hi> The Plants live, grow, flouriſh and fructifie by a Material Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: The Inſects act admirably by a like Spirit: The Brutes act ſenſibly and knowingly by a like Spirit: <hi>ergo,</hi> Man may perform all his natural Functions by the like means of a Material Spirit, inſpiring and acting the proper Organs which God hath made apt for ſuch purpoſes. We ſee, in a Muſical Organ, every Pipe hath its proper Sound and Function, and the ſame Breath acts them all; and therein appears a great Effect and Power of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Motion, rightly fabricated, and acted by the hand of Artiſts: and what then may not God do with them and by them, when he pleaſeth?</p>
            <p>I take a ſecond Exception to his ſaying, there is <hi>ſomething in Man's Compoſition that thinks, argues,</hi> &amp;c. He ſays there is no Man ſo ſceptical as to deny this, or to doubt of it; but his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake is great in it: for I do believe, that there is not any <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular thing</hi> in Man's compoſition that <hi>thinks, argues, &amp;c.</hi> but that it is the <hi>Man</hi> himſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> the whole Compoſition of Soul and Body by a divine and admirable Contexture united, which thinks, argues, and doth all other natural things, which God hath given him a Power and Propenſity to do. It is not the Preacher's <hi>ſomething in Man</hi> that doth all thoſe things which he mentions; but it is the <hi>Man</hi> that doth them, not that <hi>ſomething</hi> which he will ſurmiſe to be the Soul, for that cannot act without the bodily Organs, not think without the Brain, nor remember without the Organ of Memory, any more than ſee without an Eye, or ſpeak without a Tongue, or generate without a proper Organ for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And this needs be no news to our Preacher, for his Maſter <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> in his treatiſe of the <hi>Soul, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. counts it a great impropriety of ſpeaking to ſay, that the <hi>Soul</hi> is <hi>ſorrowful, fearful, ſenſitive</hi> or <hi>rational, angry</hi> or the like; and that one may ſay as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107183:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>properly, that the Soul <hi>weaves</hi> or <hi>builds;</hi> and that it is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to ſay, the <hi>Soul</hi> learns or reaſons, but the <hi>Man</hi> doth ſo, <hi>viz.</hi> the whole <hi>Compoſitum</hi> of Soul and Body doth them: further he ſaith there, <hi>To love, hate, think, or uſe reaſon, are not properly Affections or Actions of the Soul, but of him who hath the Soul.</hi> In his 1. <hi>cap. dicti Lib.</hi> he queſtions whether the Soul have any Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections or Actions, not communicated to the <hi>Compoſitum</hi> or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but kept as peculiar to itſelf. Finally he ſays, <hi>It ſeems to him, that the Soul hath neither Deſire, Anger, Fear,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>nor can do or ſuffer by them without the Body; nor that it can ſo much as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive or be ſenſible without it: the very Intellect,</hi> he thinks, <hi>either is the Phanſie, or cannot be acted without it, and then cannot the Soul uſe it without help of the bodily Organs. Dicaearchus</hi> maintains his Maſter's doctrine in this point, and <hi>Pliny</hi> in his Natural Hiſtory, <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 55. ſays the like, <hi>Shew if you can,</hi> ſays he, <hi>what is the Subſtance and Body of the Soul?</hi> (as it were) <hi>what kind of Matter is it apart from the Body? where lieth the Cogitation which ſhe hath? how doth ſhe ſee or hear? what toucheth ſhe? nay, what one thing doth ſhe? how is ſhe employed? or if there be none of all this in her, what good can be to her without them? ſurely theſe are but Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations of Men, who fain would live always. And there is the like Foolery in preſerving of Mens Dead Bodies: yea, ſuch is the Folly and Vanity of Men, that they think the human Soul extends [naturally] to future Ages; and that Ghoſts ſeparated from their Bodies have Senſe, and thereupon render Men them honour and worſhip; making a God of him who is not ſo much as a Man; as if the manner of Mens Breathing dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd from that of other Creatures.</hi> Theſe were all perſons eminently learn'd, and yet they denied that Man's Powers were acted by any particular or ſpecifical <hi>ſomething</hi> that was in him; and affirmed (as I do) that all are Actions of the <hi>Compoſitum,</hi> or the Man, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture of Soul and Body; and by no means can our Preacher's <hi>ſomething</hi> perform ſuch Offices, without the divine and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Contexture of Soul and Body: for that the one of theſe without the other can do no ſuch things, nor can probably do or ſuffer anything at all.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:107183:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 14. Our Preacher ſays, <hi>Such Powers and Actions muſt have an Efficient Cauſe;</hi> and I grant it, and aſſign the Contexture of Soul and Body in Man, as the Efficient and proper Cauſe of all ſuch Actions. Then he ſays, that <hi>Cogitation, Volition and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation are neither inherent in Matter as ſuch, nor acquirable to Matter by any Motion or Modification of it.</hi> To this I anſwer, that Senſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Perception are inherent in Man and Beaſt, and to each of them belonging, as they are divine Compoſitions, or rather Contextures, of Soul and Body. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. ſays <hi>God formed Man of the duſt of the ground;</hi> ſo c. 3. v. 19. God ſays to Man, <hi>out of the ground waſt thou taken, for duſt thou art and to duſt ſhalt thou return.</hi> We know that human Arts have ſo far prevailed as to communicate to dead and hard Matter a fixed and regular Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Witneſs <hi>Architas</hi> his Dove, and <hi>Regiomontanus</hi> his Eagle, both made of Wood, and a Fly of Iron made by the laſt, who all flew at their full liberty in the Air, to a certain and conſiderable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and returned in a regular manner to the places from whence they firſt ſet out; and this, Men would not then believe could be done without an Immaterial Spirit; that theſe Engines therefore were moved by Daemons, and the Artiſts were Conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, was a common opinion of thoſe times, and hitherto Artiſts are with Difficulty defended from ſuch Imputations. Dr. <hi>Willis</hi> in his <hi>Anima Brutorum</hi> p. 40. <hi>De illis redarguendis ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus non ſum, qui viventium ſenſus &amp; facultates quaſcunque percepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vas, non niſi à ſubſtantia immateriali immortalique obire poſſe conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt;</hi> he ſays, He did not think ſuch Thinkers worthy of any anſwer; and this perhaps might be his reaſon for it, he knew that our Preacher's Affertion was maintained by ſeveral learned Men, but after a different mode of Argumentation: for when they were preſs'd by the Argument taken from the Actions and Faculties of the Brutes, <hi>viz.</hi> that they have and act as many Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as Men have, and uſe them as perfectly, that they have as ſtrong and active Affections, Paſſions, Appetites and local Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as Men have; that they have Phanſie, Memory and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivance, like thoſe of Men, tho in far lower degrees than thoſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107183:3"/>of Men are. Upon averment that all theſe Faculties in the Brutes were acted by a material Spirit, and a demand why the ſame might not be effected amongſt Men: the Maintainers of Immateriality ſeem much put to it for an anſwer to this Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and they are divided upon it: ſome of them ſay, that Brutes have neither Senſes, nor Affections, nor Appetites, nor any ſort of Perceivances at all, and that they know no more of what they do, than the Organ-pipes know when they make Muſick, or a pair of Bellows that they blow the Fire; whence they would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, that they have not, and need not, any ſort of Soul, for that they neither uſe nor have any ſenſible Faculty at all. But this Argument appears to me, as I ſuppoſe it did to Dr. <hi>Willis, argumentum ducens ad abſurdum,</hi> and therefore but a Fallacy. For what can lightly appear more abſurd to the common ſenſe of Mankind, than boldly and ſeriouſly to affirm that a Dog or a Horſe doth neither hear, ſee, ſmell, taſte, nor even feel, when they are whipt, ſpurr'd or beaten; and that Beaſts have neither Love, Wrath, Fear, Expectation or Deſire; theſe Aſſertions ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo contrary to Mens daily experience, and therefore ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd as to make Dr. <hi>Willis</hi> think ſuch Arguers deſerve no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: and yet <hi>Des Cartes</hi> and Sir <hi>K. Digby</hi> profeſs to argue on that ſide, and thereby to ſupport the neceſſary Immateriality of a human Soul. Others there are who, to ſupport the neceſſity of ſuch an Immateriality, take a quite different and even a contrary courſe; for obſerving the infirmity and abſurdity of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited Argument, they agree and acknowledge, that Brutes have and uſe all their Senſes, Affections, Paſſions, Appetites and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Motions as Men uſe them; and that they have and uſe Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, Memory, Perceivance and Choice, like, but in a much low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er degree than thoſe of Men: but, ſay they, the Brutes cannot thus act without the aſſiſtance and guidance of Spirits or Souls; nay, and that it is not a Material Soul which can ſerve for ſuch purpoſes, but that Brutes muſt of neceſſity be reputed to have Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>material Souls, praeexiſtent before they came into their brutal Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and that ſhall ſubſiſt in a ſtate of Separation after the death
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107183:4"/>of ſuch brutal Bodies: And this they ſay and affirm, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to perſuade, that there is an abſolute neceſſity for Men to have Immaterial Souls; becauſe, ſay they, the very Brutes cannot act their Senſes and Faculties without ſuch Souls. And theſe were ſuch Arguers as Dr <hi>Willis</hi> thought not to deſerve his Anſwer: and yet Dr. <hi>More</hi> aſſerts this opinion in <hi>terminis;</hi> and <hi>Baxter</hi> follows the ſame very near, altho not altogether ſo fully. But they are all eagerly bent to eſtabliſh the Immateriality, and Immortality of Human Souls; for fear, that otherwiſe there would not be a ſufficient ground or foundation for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of Rewards and Puniſhments future to this Life; not enough remembring or conſidering the Article of the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and the laſt Judgment, appointed by God for that very purpoſe of diſtributing Recompences according to the behaviour which Men have uſed in paſſing through the Trials and Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of this World.</p>
            <p>Our Preacher inſiſts, <hi>That if Senſation were inherent in Matter, Stocks and Stones would be Percipient and Rational Creatures.</hi> To this, I ſay, that may be competent to, and inherent in one ſort of Matter, which is very incompetent to, and incoherent with, another ſort of Matter. But he ſeems to intend a confounding all ſorts of Matter together, as if Logs, Metals, and Stones, were of the ſame nature with Fleſh, Blood and Brain, or thoſe of Water, Air and Fire; amongſt all which ſorts of Matter, I ſay, there are very great Differences; and ſome of theſe ſorts of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter are capable of ſuch Effects and Operations, as others of them are not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 15. <hi>Aimed only againſt Atheiſts,, and ſuch as deny there are any Spiritual Subſtunces.</hi> I ſay thereunto, I am not of that Belief or Opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 17. He ſays, <hi>Matter cannot acquire Motion of it ſelf.</hi> This I deny: For I ſay, that Wind and Fire are Matter, and yet Self-movers; nor do they, or can they, ever loſe their Motion, or ceaſe moving ſo long as they continue to be Wind or Fire. And if we ſhall conſider the Duſt of which <hi>Adam</hi> was made, we
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107183:4"/>may find that it may be ſo comminuted and refined, as when pounced through a fine Searce, the ſmalleſt part of it will riſe up again like a thin cloud, aſcending upwards of itſelf, and apt to be moved with every little Breath; reſembling, and fine as thoſe Atoms which we call Motes in the Sun, and which of their own nature maintain a perpetual Motion. It ſeems a Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum of ſuch active Particles impregnated with rorid Steams and Juices apt to aſcend by adhering to any ſolid Body, are not apt alone for Motion, but that by the hand and skill of a Divine Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt there may be made of ſuch like Ingredients, a Cogitative Matter. For an inſtance of which, we may propound the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſects, who have nothing but mere earth and duſt impregnated for their Originals, and yet act regularly, and according to the Rules and Directions of Art and Science; witneſs the Bees, the Ants, and the admirable Textures of the Spiders; God thereby revealing to us, that he can, out of mere Matter, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Arts and Sciences, and eſpecially for the preſervation and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of his Creatures: but far beyond the Practiſe or Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Men to perform, and even their Powers to conceive or apprehend the true and next reaſons or cauſes of ſuch Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances: To ſuch purpoſe <hi>Phil. Melanchthon, lib. de anima, p.</hi> 20. He had juſt before recited, <hi>Certas deſcriptiones Philiſophicas, quae ſi de pecudis anima tantum quaereretur, utcunque monſtrarent, aliquid quod cogitari poteſt in materia fons eſſe actionum: nondum tamen penitus haec perſpicimus, &amp; cur ita factum ſit ſapientia eſt artificis, non noſtra.</hi> Pag. 112. he ſays, <hi>Maxime admirandum eſt cerebrum, quod eſt domicilium, ac officina cogitationum.</hi> And altho we do not thorowly know the Subſtance and Operation of the Brain, nor the <hi>ubi</hi> or, <hi>quomodo</hi> ſuch things are wrought in it, but muſt leave ſuch Knowledge to the Wiſdom of the Creator: Yet thus much, ſays he, <hi>Men may know of it; oriri ejus materiam à ſubtiliſſima parte ſeminis &amp; plena ſpirituum, quae in formatione foetus; in illam hominis arcem ſummam quaſi exaeſtuat, cum epar, cor, &amp; venulae inchoantur.</hi> And this derivation of the Brain, and its daily and known Performances, make it look very like a <hi>mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107183:5"/>Cogitativa;</hi> and as ſuch it ſhall be left here, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Author the Preachers pretences to the contrary.</p>
            <p>In this page he handles Matter, as if three of the Elements, <hi>viz.</hi> Water, Air, and Fire were no parts of Matter; which I paſs for an apparent miſtake: And he ſays, Matter cannot ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire Motion of itſelf without thruſting of ſome other Body, or intrinſical Motion of an immaterial Spirit. This is denied be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and inſtances given of the Wind and Fire, which move themſelves and other things about them, during the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of their own being.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 18. He ſays, <hi>no parts of Matter, conſidered in themſelves, are hot or cold, white or black, bitter or ſweet; and that they have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther light or colour, heat or ſound; theſe are not,</hi> ſays he, <hi>in Bodies abſolutely conſidered, but in our Eyes, Ears, and other Organs of Senſe.</hi> I anſwer, <hi>Quod non ego credulus illi;</hi> I grant Men cannot perceive ſuch qualities in Matter but by means of their Senſes, but withal do believe that there are Light, and Bodies illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating, tho Men ſhould not ſee them; ſo Sounds not heard, ſo Heat without Mens feeling it, diſcoverable enough by ſeeing it at a diſtance, conſumption of the fewel, and the ſcorcht blackneſs of ſuch parts of the fewel as are left after ſuch a fire. But yet he will prove what he ſaid to be true, by an inſtance: <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>If glaſs that hath no colour at all, be broke and braid into ſmall parcels, thoſe ſmall parcels will look to be of a white colour, and yet truly they have no more colour in them than they had before, and that truly is none at all.</hi> I grant him there is in this inſtance a <hi>deceptio viſus,</hi> and that the thing appears otherwiſe than it is: Shall it be concluded, that becauſe our Senſes are deceived in ſome things, therefore we cannot truſt them in any thing? there ſeems ſmall foundation for ſuch a concluſion. And I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon put him another inſtance, <hi>viz. Put a ſtrait Stick into the water, preſently it will appear crooked, but take it out, and it will look ſtrait again, and was always ſo notwithſtanding its appearance.</hi> He may as well pretend to infer, that there are really no crooked ſticks
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107183:5"/>in Nature, as that Matter hath no real Qualities becauſe Men are deceived, in thinking his bray'd-Glaſs to be white. And yet he ſays, <hi>P.</hi> 19. <hi>That he hath ſufficiently proved his Aſſertion:</hi> But I beg his pardon, for thinking he is miſtaken. He ſays there, <hi>That the Qualities in Bodies can no more be conceived to be real, than Roſes or Honey can be thought to ſmell and taſte their own ſweetneſs.</hi> Had he ſaid, than Roſes have a ſweet ſmell, or Honey a ſweet taſte, the ſaying might have been both coherent and true; whereas now it ſeems to be neither.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 20. He pretends to believe, and perſuade, that the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Man is a Senſeleſs piece of Matter, which hath neither colour, warmth, ſoftneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He ſays, he hath proved this, but I do not know where; and I beg his pardon for not believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him; For I muſt adhere to <hi>Thomas Didymus</hi> againſt him, truſting my own Senſes in their healthy and ſound Condition, to judge of their proper Objects, placed at a reaſonable diſtance, and the fitting Sphere of their Activity, and aſſiſted by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Powers of Human Perception or Judgment; which eaſily diſcovers, that the Sight is deceived, when it takes his bray'd-Glaſs to be really white, or my Stick in the water to be really crooked. He ſays farther, <hi>It is not Blood and Bones that can judge, nor can the Head or Brain do it, as being only Body, and not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginative.</hi> P. 21. But, ſays he, <hi>Our oppoſers may reply, [and ſo they do] That the Animal Spirits, and Inſenſible Particles there reſiding,</hi> [viz. <hi>in the Head and Brain</hi>] <hi>do actuate the common Senſe, Phancy, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, Judgment and other Powers of the Underſtanding.</hi> To this he replies, <hi>the thing cannot be ſo; for that their Spirits muſt have each a determinate Figure, as Cubes, Spheres, Cones,</hi> &amp;c. But this is not granted him; for I ſay rather, that theſe Spirits in the Head are Particles of the pureſt Blood Inflamed, glowing and lucid, irradiating the Brain, and all the Ventricles or Concavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of it, with the appendances of Apprehenſion and Memory thereunto belonging. He ſays, <hi>We do not grind inanimate Corn into Living and Rational Meal: and that Nails, Hair, Horns and Hoofs, may bid as fair for Underſtanding as the fineſt Animl Spirit
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107183:6"/>of them all.</hi> To this I anſwer, That the inflamed glowing Particles of Blood, called Spirits, are not in themſelves Sentient or Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, but they are the <hi>Actus primus corporis Organici, viz.</hi> The Active Principle of Life, Motion, Senſe and Underſtanding in Man and Beaſt; ſtimulating and acting every Part and Organ of the Body to the performance of thoſe Duties for which by the Great Creator they were intended and made. Thoſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits therefore Act the Eye to ſee, the Ear to hear, the Tongue to ſpeak, the Liver to make blood, the Heart to purifie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine it, the Underſtanding or Brain to apprehend, judge and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member: It cannot make one Organ perform the Function of another Organ, but acts every Organ according to its proper Uſe and natural Capacity, And therefore it is not the Soul or the Body that act, inable, or govern the Man, but the Man, by the activity of his Soul, and the aptitude of his bodily Organs, doth all thoſe things which we daily ſee are done amongſt us, not by Soul or Body ſingly, but by the Virtues and Contexture of both together.</p>
            <p>For his ſaying, <hi>that Men cannot grind Corn into Living and Rational Meal:</hi> If it have a meaning, it ſeems to intend, that Corn cannot be ſo uſed as to effect Life and Rationality in Men; and if it be taken in that ſenſe, the opinion ſeems to be a very clear mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake: For every days Experience ſhews, that Corn ground and made into Bread is one of the ſtrongeſt ſupports of Life, both for Man and Beaſt; that concocted in the Stomach, is convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Blood in the Liver, purified in the Heart, ſent thence by the Arteries into the Head and Brain, where becoming a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit inflam'd and lucid, it acts in all the Organs, the Powers of Life, Motion, Senſes, and Underſtanding. And if ſuch Corn be Brewed into Drink, we know it may be made ſo ſpirited, as a little of it will very much revive, quicken and cheriſh the Natural Faculties of Man and Beaſt, and particulary the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning and rational Powers of Mankind, in increaſing activity and mettle both in Body and Soul. We ſay of Wine, <hi>Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107183:6"/>ſumptum acuit ingenium.</hi> 1 <hi>Eſdras</hi> 3. <hi>Wine makes the mind of a Beggar equal to that of a King, and turns every thought into jollity.</hi> This grows from the ſubtilty and activity of that Liquor, and the many and ſtrong Spirits which are in it, apt to take fire and be inflamed, and to burn till the whole Spirit of it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed. And the Soul Material, is not only refreſh'd and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened by Corn and Wine, as well as the Body; but the Soul generally of any ſort, material or immaterial, cannot live or continue in the Body without Breath, Blood, and daily or ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Nouriſhment. For the Blood, <hi>Moſes</hi> calls it, <hi>the life of the creature;</hi> and ſays, <hi>the life is in the blood, and as the life it makes atonement upon the Altar.</hi> As to the Breath, all Men know that if it be ſtopt but for a few moments, the Soul, if Material, will be extinguiſhed, and if Immaterial, will be diſlodged and driven away from its Body, not able to ſubſiſt there (even for a ſhort time) without breath; which, how it ſhould be ſo very needful for an Immaterial Soul I cannot conceive. Well, but farther, the Man muſt have daily, or ſufficient Nouriſhment, or elſe the Soul, as well as the Body, will find want of it, and the Man will decay by degrees, till for want of a ſupply, death and diſſolution muſt follow, if a ſupply be not had in time competent. We read 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30. that <hi>David</hi> at <hi>Ziklag</hi> found an <hi>Egyptian</hi> in the field famiſhed, for he had neither eaten nor drunk in three days and three nights; but they gave him Fruit and Water, upon which the Man's <hi>Spirit came again to him:</hi> ſo <hi>Judg.</hi> 15. <hi>Sampſon</hi> ready to die for thirſt, pray'd, and God clave a hollow place in the Jaw-bone, and there came water thereout, and when <hi>Sampſon</hi> had drunk, <hi>his Spirit came again and he revived.</hi> In both theſe caſes, if neceſſary Nouriſhment had not come in due time, the Perſons had died: for upon nouriſhment they revived, and <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>'s Spirit came again to him and he revived. I demand what ſort of Spirit was this which came again and revived <hi>Sampſon?</hi> it ſeems not one that was Immaterial, becauſe that needs not, nor is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of nouriſhment: and therefore I conclude it was a Material Spirit, which needed Nouriſhment, and was capable of being
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107183:7"/>refreſhed and revived by it, as adding new Fuel for ſupporting the flame of Life almoſt extinguiſhed for want of needful Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment. And yet, upon this revival, we find the <hi>Egyptians</hi> Underſtanding, Memory and Senſes were preſently recovered, of which before his eating he had little or no uſe at all. Whence it appears, that rational Powers are acted by this Spirit, which depends upon Nouriſhment, as failing and reviving with it. And from all this, it ſeems one may venture to conclude that Corn may be converted into a living and rational Activity, as being a proper Nouriſhment for Man and Beaſt, and for their Bodies and Souls, one as well as the other; as being ſo for the Man, who is a Contexture of both.</p>
            <p>His ſix next Pages, <hi>viz.</hi> from 22 to 28, are intended to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute thoſe who affirm, that the great or little Worlds were not created by God, but that they derive themſelves from an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental Concourſe and Coheſion of Atoms. That all were the Works of God, I am ready to grant, and to maintain, as well as he; but in his deſign to prove God's Providence and Creation by the Immateriality of human Souls, I judge he hath taken a wrong Sow by the ear. The Creation of the World by God, I grant to be true; that the human Soul is Immaterial, I hold not to be true: and I can but be ſorry to find our Preacher fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into the Inconvenience of endeavouring to prove that which is true, by that which perhaps is not true.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 28. He ſays, <hi>Men will object, the Powers and Actions of ſome Brutes nearly approaching to human Reaſon, and with ſome viſible Glimpſes of Underſtanding; and ſay they, if theſe things can be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the pure Mechaniſm of their Bodies, then it is but raiſing our Conceptions, and ſuppoſing Men to be Engines of a finer make and contexture, and the buſineſs is done; for then the Objectors will ſay, there needs no Immaterial Soul, nor any Soul at all, for the acting of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Faculties, but the Mechaniſm of human Bodies ſhould be enough to act their Faculties, and perform all that by Men is uſually and naturally performed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 29. He quotes the other Opinion, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Brutes have degrees of Reaſon, and their full Senſes, and Affections, and Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107183:7"/>and therefore have Souls, and thoſe Immaterial.</hi> Our Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher paſſes over both theſe Opinions as very indifferent things to him, which of them be true, or whether either or neither of them be ſo. I have ſhewn before that both theſe Opinions are erroneous, which he thought not fit to aſſert here, where it ſeems he properly ought to have done it, altho I doubt not but that he believes them to be ſo. He ſays <hi>We need not be concerned about the Truth in this point, viz.</hi> whether the Brutes are Machines, or have Immortal Souls: but I ſay, if either of theſe Opinions be true, the whole Fabrick of Nature and Science would thereby be drawn into very great Differences and Alterations, and the point is not indifferent to others, whatſoever it be to him. Well, <hi>but,</hi> ſays he, <hi>if Men be Machines, they can have neither Reaſon nor Senſe.</hi> He ſhould have gone on and ſaid, but we know that Men have Senſe and Reaſon, and therefore they are not bare Machines (as ſome pretend to make men believe:) but inſtead of that fairer and truer Inference, it pleaſes him to deliver a Paradoxical and falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Axiom of his own, uncoherently enough introduced, <hi>viz. Omnipotency it ſelf cannot create cogitative Body, becauſe of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacity in the Subject.</hi> I have before ſpoken concerning Earth pulverized and rarified into the tenuity of a Cloud, impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſteams and juices no leſs, but more fine and active than the Vegetable Souls or Spirits of Plants, mixed and irrigated, and, as it were, ſteep'd and ſoak'd by and with innumerable Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vages and Sources, proceeding from Fountains and Ciſterns, with which the outward World daily communicates, for ſupplying the daily Decays of them. I conceive Matter thus conſtituted, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnated, irrigated and enlivened, may, by Divine Power, be made cogitative. That the Inſects work according to Rules of Art and Science, I know none who can obſerve them and deny it: that Brutes have their Senſes, Affections, Paſſions, Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites and Motions, all Men do grant, but the moſt blind and wilful among the <hi>Carteſians;</hi> alſo that they have Phanſie, Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Perceivances, acted in and by their Brains, and Dr. <hi>Willis dict. lib. p.</hi> 59. ſays, <hi>in Hominibus &amp; Brutis eadem prorſus eſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formatio
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107183:8"/>organorum animalium.</hi> And the Evidences that Cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and all other rational Acts in Men, depend upon the Brain, and are performed in it and by it, ſeem to me ſo clear and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable, as that joined to the reſt it may paſs for a ſtrong Proof, that the Brain of Man is cogitative Matter, or very like it.</p>
            <p>And as to his phraſing it, that <hi>Omnipotence it ſelf cannot make cogitative Body,</hi> there may be applied a Saying of Dr. <hi>Willis, p.</hi> 5. ſuch Men it ſeems do think, <hi>quod Deus nihil amplius fabricare vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, quam quod homo poſſit concipere aut effingere.</hi> Well, but our Preacher ſays, this cannot be done <hi>becauſe of the Incapacity of the Subject;</hi> to this I anſwer, that <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Rod laid upon the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle was dry Wood, and ſeemed to be under an incapacity of bearing Fruit; and yet in the morning, by Divine Power, it had budded, and brought forth Bloſſoms and yielded Almonds: the Red Sea ſtood like Walls, and <hi>Jordan</hi> ſtaid its Waters from run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning downwards: the <hi>Chaldean</hi> Fire forbore to burn God's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, or ſo much as to ſinge their Cloths; all which are Acts beyond the natural Capacities of the Agents of them: and ſo was the multiplying of the Loaves and Fiſhes, under the Goſpel: and what will our Preacher ſay to <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.24. Hath a Camel the Capacity of going through the Eye of a needle? Chriſt ſays, with Men this is impoſſible, but not with God, for with him all things are poſſible; whence it ſeems poſſible with him to make cogitative Body, notwithſtanding our Preachers aſſurance to the contrary.</p>
            <p>That the cogitative Power very much depends upon the good Diſpoſition, Soundneſs and Temperament of the Brain, is a thing ſo well known as it ſeems to need very little confirmation. <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 146.3. ſays, <hi>When the breath of man goeth forth he ſhall turn again to his earth, and then all his thoughts periſh,</hi> the new Tranſlation reads, <hi>Mans breath goeth forth, he returns to his earth, and that very day his thoughts periſh.</hi> The periſhing of his Thoughts may be expounded his Intentions or Deſigns; but more literal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fully, it ſeems to intend the Man's power and faculty of Thinking, for the Man dead can think no more. But what is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107183:8"/>it that dies? our Preacher will deny that his Soul dies; and yet by Death the Man's Faculty of Thinking is certainly deſtroyed; <hi>viz.</hi> by Death of the Body, and the Parts and Organs of it, <hi>ergo,</hi> the Body or ſome Organs of it are <hi>materia cogitativa.</hi> And the ſame may be further proved <hi>ex principiis:</hi> for during Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and whilſt the cogitative Parts and Organs are immature, we think like Children, but grown to maturity we put away childiſh Thoughts or modes of Thinking: and yet then, if the Brain happen to be clouded with Fumes from the Spleen or other Diſtempers, or even by thoſe from Wine or Strong-drink, the Man cannot think orderly or rationally; and in phrenetick Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers Mens Thoughts rave and rove without Order or any Coherence or Connexion at all: in Diſeaſes where the Head is ſtupified, as Apoplexies, the Man becomes temporally incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of any Thoughts at all. From all which I collect, that the Particles of Blood inflamed, aſcending from the Heart unto the Head, are there further rarified, and made lucid, irradiating the Brain, and the Ventricles thereof; and that to theſe Spirits and Organs God hath imparted a diſcerning Faculty or Power, and that when theſe Organs are ſound and perfect, and the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Particles clear, bright and lucid, they work to a perfection of degrees in the Minds, Reaſon and Thoughts of Men; unto which God adds, when he pleaſes, <hi>afflatum divini numinis,</hi> and that accumulates an excellency of Perfection to Man, and in him, of thinking, inventing and diſcerning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 31. Our Preacher ſays, he hath ſufficiently ſhewn that <hi>Senſe and Perception can never be the product of any kind of Matter or Motion.</hi> And if this be true, let our Readers make themſelves the Judges. Well, <hi>but,</hi> ſays he, <hi>if this cannot be corporeal, it muſt come from an incorporeal Subſtance within us.</hi> If he will take a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Spirit for an incorporeal Subſtance, we are agreed; but if he will have this incorporeal Subſtance to be an immaterial, intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, angelical Spirit, I anſwer, he hath not proved the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of its being ſo, nor that the thing is ſo; nay here he confeſſes, we cannot conceive the manner of our Souls Action
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107183:9"/>and Paſſion, nor what hold it can lay on the Body, when it vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily moves it: this is what we cannot conceive of ſuch a Soul. But I deſire him to tell us what he doth conceive or know concerning ſuch a Soul; that he will evince to Reaſon, <hi>quod ſit! quid ſit? unde oritur? quando ingreditur? ubi reſidet? quomodo operatur? an ſeparatim ſubſiſtit? quo avolat deficiente corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re?</hi> If he can teach ſcientifically concerning theſe Points, his word will be better taken in many other things; and yet even then I could hardly credit his next Aſſertion, <hi>viz. tho we cannot conceive the Soul nor its Actings, yet we are as certain of them as of any Mathematical Truth whatſoever, which I both can conceive, and may be eaſily demonſtrated to me.</hi> The Truth and Reaſonableneſs of this Aſſertion ſhall be left to thoſe who are at leiſure to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 32. He confeſſes his Ignorance in cauſes of Mens Pleaſure, Pain, Sleep, Activity, he ſays, <hi>this Knowledge exceeds Man's narrow Faculties, and is out of the reach of our Diſcovery:</hi> he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns excellent Final Cauſes of the vital Conjunction of Body and Soul, but the Inſtrumental he knows not, nor how they are united or tied together; he reſolves all into God's good Pleaſure; but he ſhews us no Evidence that it is, or ever was, his Pleaſure, to inform Mankind by an Immaterial, Intelligent Spirit, which is capable of living in a State of Separation from the Body. And if Corporeal Powers be confeſſedly too hard for him, it may ſeem ſtrange he ſhould attempt upon the Diſquiſition, concerning the Being and Operations of an Immaterial Soul in Man, without ſo much as offering to make any poſitive proof of the Thing, from the Grounds either of Reaſon or Scripture. I am not able to credit his bare Word for it, nor his negative proof, that it muſt be ſo, becauſe he thinks it cannot be otherwiſe. Theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſions ſeem of ſmall force, with thoſe who think the thing may be otherwiſe, and is truly ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 35. He thinks, that for Men to deny the Soul, becauſe they cannot ſee, or any ways perceive it, is not reaſonable: and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:107183:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>it ſeems to me full as unreaſonable to prove that man hath an Immaterial Soul, becauſe God cannot create Cogitative Body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 36. He ſays, <hi>He neither can, nor will command God to come from Heaven to conſume his oppoſers.</hi> It is well he owns the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of his power, and it may be, that therefore he will not do it: For that page 26. he ſays, <hi>Banging and Buffeting into Reaſon is the moſt proper and effectual to be uſed againſt his oppoſers: It is,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the vigorous Execution of good Laws, and not Rational Diſcourſes only, that muſt be uſed to reclaim ſuch profane Perſous.</hi> He means Laws ſo good as to Eſtabliſh his Opinion, and ſet ſharp Penalties upon all others who dare profeſs to believe otherwiſe. So did <hi>Saul,</hi> he haled Men and Women and committed them to Priſon, becauſe they believed, and worſhipt after a way which he thought Hereſie. So did the old <hi>Romans;</hi> and ſo do the Romaniſts, the Turks, and the <hi>French</hi> King; are all of our Preachers mind, <hi>viz.</hi> The Opinion which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails and hath moſt worldly Power ſhall do beſt, to make ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Laws with ſharp Penalties againſt their competitors; and this is all that Men can do: And this our Preacher de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires ſhould be done on the behalf of his Opinion; and this courſe detects firſt his own Inclination: and next, that he hath no great confidence in the force of his own Argument; ſeeing he ſays, Perſecution and Puniſhment are the only means likely to prevail for reducing his oppoſers from their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Errors, forgetting the old Obſervation, <hi>Hodie mihi, cras tibi;</hi> the Opinion cried up to day, may fall to morrow: He who thinks he ſtands may fall: and therefore our Lord's dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is wiſe and good, <hi>as ye would men ſhould do unto you, even ſo do ye unto them.</hi> And in Miſtakes of the Judgmedt, Men ſhould remember, that <hi>none can come to Chriſt but whom the Father draws,</hi> which it ſeems ſhould paſs for an Argument inducing Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Forbearance towards our miſtaken, and therefore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Brethren, in Opinions which do not induce, or encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to an ill Practice or Courſe of Life.</p>
            <p>Thus have I traced our Preacher, and followed him with Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation through all the Pages of his Sermon, which concern
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107183:10"/>the Immateriality of a human Soul. His Promiſe made <hi>P.</hi> 13. to prove there is an Immaterial Soul in Man, ſeems ſomewhat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily performed, and very unſucceſsfully; for he offers no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Proof at all, and his negative Proof ſeems very inſufficient for the ſupport of ſo great a Streſs and Burthen as he hath laid upon it. And it ſhall be left to the Opinion of our Peruſers whether he have well performed his bold Undertaking and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe or not. Ready however to accept of and to deſire a future performance of that which yet ſeems to be inſufficiently attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted. He ſaid, <hi>I will prove there is an Immaterial Soul in Man.</hi> I think this Sermon to be no performance of this Promiſe; and I do not believe that our Preacher hath ſaid all, nor the beſt that he is able to ſpeak to that purpoſe: he may conſider an honeſt Man ought to be as good as his word, and what he performs not at one time he will endeavour to effect at another, as far as his Power or Talent can be extended. What he hath done to that purpoſe in this Sermon, ſeems to me very infirm and little conſiderable, as depending upon Mens opinions what God is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do. Our Lord himſelf tells us, that <hi>with God all things are poſſible;</hi> and it ſeems ſomewhat an odd Aſſertion, that the Inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of Matter ſhould hinder God from making what he will out of it; whereas it ſeems rather, that he who made Matter out of nothing, can make any thing out of any Matter, and many other things than Men can imagine; and the moſt Miracles are acted either contrary to, or above and beyond the natural Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities of the Agents therein imployed. If the thing which he promiſed to prove be really true, it ſeems he ſtands engaged for the Proof of it, in the beſt manner and with the beſt ſtrength he is able, aſſiſted by his Reading, Contemplation and Conference. The Point is of weighty Conſideration, and he hath built upon it the Power and Providence of a Deity; whence it ſeems he ſtands engaged to make good the Immateriality of a human Soul, and its Subſiſtence in a ſeparate ſtate from the Body. This if ſcientifically he can and does do, or with any apparent probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, he ſhall be <hi>Magnus Apollo,</hi> and receive Commendations ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly; and if he fail or fall ſhort in the Attempt, no more
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107183:10"/>will be ſaid by his preſent Opponent, than <hi>magnis excidit auſis:</hi> as <hi>magnum,</hi> there is glory in the Undertaking, and that he may not <hi>excidere auſis,</hi> his beſt Forces are to be employed in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of that ſervice to the Church and to the World. In this Sermon he hath forborn the Quotation of Scripture, as diſputing with Perſons who refuſed to accept the Authority of it: but if he ſhall think fit to ſtick to his word, and to prove or endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to prove, that the human Soul is an Immaterial, Intelligent Spirit, he will therein have to do with ſome who are ready to ſubmit to the Rules and Authority of Scripture, and to be tried by them, as well as by the Rules and Experiments extracted from Nature and Reaſon: he will then, I hope, make uſe of that Holy Book to fortifie his Tenet, and <hi>deſcendere in arenam,</hi> armed with his beſt Forces drawn out of all Gariſons and Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zines, fit for ſuch a deſign; ſo may his Proof appear in the beſt manner that he can perform it; and why not in the beſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that the ſame can be performed? my deſire is to ſee it done in ſuch manner; ready to ſubmit to Truth made viſible in any intelligible manner whatſoever. We have learnt, that <hi>whatſoever doth make manifeſt is Light;</hi> the preſent Sermon ſeems to have little of that Light which manifeſts; but I expect that when he ſhall undertake to write <hi>ex profeſſo</hi> upon this ſubject, and to make full proof of his Aſſertion according to his promiſe, that then his Arguments ſhall place Truth in ſo good a Light, and ſet it out in ſuch natural and lively Colours, as thereby ſhe may be eaſily diſcovered for what ſhe is. And upon ſuch a Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, no Man well meaning and intelligent, who dare truſt his Faculties, but will be ready with open Arms to accept and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace her whom all profeſs to ſeek; tho too many, with <hi>Ixion</hi>'s Fate, embrace a Cloud inſtead of <hi>Juno.</hi> My Meaning is to confide, in ſome Meaſure, that he will endeavour to perform his quoted Promiſe, in the beſt manner that he is able; and thereupon my deſire ſhall be, that Truth may be his Aim; and that ſhe may fulfil what <hi>Eſdras</hi> declares of her, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>She may endure, be ſtrong, and live, and conquer for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
